Guide to the William Makepeace Thackeray Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Makepeace Thackeray collection
1846-1912
GEN MSS 1101
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.75
(3 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, and drawings by or related to William Makepeace Thackeray. Correspondence includes letters written by Thackeray to colleagues such as Connop Thirlwall and William Webb Follett Synge, and letters to Thackeray from potential conributors to Cornhill Magazine. Writings include an autograph manuscript of a chapter of The Adventures of Philip, an autograph poem parodying Goethe's Werther, and an autograph manuscript notebook with memoranda, drawings, and quotations from American history, used by Thackeray while writing The Virginians. Also present are sixteen sketches in watercolor and graphite by Thackeray, two groups of ink illustrations for Thackeray's writings by John Priestman Atkinson, and a portrait of Thackeray by an unidentified artist.
Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, 1944-1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Makepeace Thackeray (1811-1863)
English novelist.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, and drawings by or related to William Makepeace Thackeray. Correspondence includes letters written by Thackeray to colleagues such as Connop Thirlwall and William Webb Follett Synge, and letters to Thackeray from potential contributors to The Cornhill Magazine. Writings include an autograph manuscript of a chapter of The Adventures of Philip, and an autograph manuscript notebook with memoranda, drawings, and quotations from American history, used by Thackeray while writing The Virginians. Also present are sixteen sketches in watercolor and graphite by Thackeray, two groups of ink illustrations for Thackeray's writings by John Priestman Atkinson, and a portrait of Thackeray by an unidentified artist.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1846-1862. II. Writings, 1853, undated. III. Drawings, 1859-1878.
Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; Sketches -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Adolphus, John Leycester, 1795-1862; Atkinson, J. Priestman; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Werther, Parodies, imitations, etc.); Ritchie, Anne Thackeray, 1837-1919; Sala, George Augustus, 1828-1895; Schachner, Joseph Rudolph, 1816-1896; Synge, W. W. Follett (William Webb Follett), 1826-1891; Thackeray, Thomas James; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Portraits; Thirlwall, Connop, 1797-1875; Castles, John W., 1893-1965 -- Bookplate; Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945 -- Bookplate; McCutcheon, George Barr, 1866-1928 -- Bookplate
- Correspondence, 1846-1862; Series I; 12
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains letters written by Thackeray to various colleagues and acquaintances, with one volume of letters written to Thackeray.
  - To John Leycester Adolphus; autograph letter, signed, 1854 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Custodial History
    Gift of Ruth Ellen du Pont Lord and Pauline Louise du Pont Harrison, 1970.
  - To Charles Bray; autograph letter, signed, 1855 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gift of Gordon S. Haight (Yale 1923 BA, 1933 PhD), 1974.
  - To Frederic Chapman; autograph letter, signed, [1850?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of Mary Poindexter Rigby Carlisle, 1955.
    General note
    Accompanied by a portrait of Thackeray engraved for the Eclectic Magazine.
  - To Miss Holmes; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchased on the Plain Fund, 1954.
  - To Peter Purcell; autograph letter, signed, 1846 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Purchased on the Elizabeth W. Manwaring Fund, 1954.
    Accompanied by four leaves and one engraved plate from Notes of a Journey from Cornhill to Grand Cairo (London: Chapman and Hall, 1846).
  - To George Augustus Sala; autograph letters (2), signed, [1862], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Purchased from Clive Farahar & Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998.
  - To Joseph Rudolph Schachner; autograph letter, signed, 1859 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Gift of Philip D. Sang, 1955.
  - To Mr. Scott; autograph letter, signed, [1857?] Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Gift of J. Miller Dixon for the Alan C. Dixon Memorial, 1944.
    Letter written in slanting hand; postscript written in upright hand.
  - To William Webb Follett Synge; autograph letter, signed with initials, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift of E. C. Jones, 1948.
    Accompanied by an engraved portrait of Thackeray by A. Weger, Liepzig.
  - To Thomas James Thackeray; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Gift of Mr. and Mrs. W. R. Blum, 1953.
    Accompanied by an etched portrait of Thackeray by G. Sidney Hunt after Samuel Laurance.
  - To Connop Thirlwall, addressed to "My dear Lord Bishop," London; autograph letter, signed, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Gift of John C. Thirlwall, 1966.
  - To Thackeray from potential contributors to the The Cornhill Magazine (1 bound volume with 14 autograph letters, signed), 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973; with bookplate of Jerome Kern.
- Writings, 1853, undated; Series II; 8
  Series II contains autograph manuscripts by Thackeray, as well as corrected proofs of some of his printed writings.
  - The Adventures of Philip on His Way Through the World, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Autograph manuscript of 2 pages of the novel.
    Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973.
  - The Adventures of Philip on His Way Through the World, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Gift of John W. Castles (Yale 1915), 1947.
    Autograph manuscript, unsigned, of a large part of Chapter XXI (6 pages). Accompanied by a small sheet containing the genealogy of Philip, in Thackeray's hand.
  - The Four Georges, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973
    Proofs in various stages of revision, corrected by the author for publication in the The Cornhill Magazine, July-October 1860; bound with two of the articles extracted from the magazine as issued.
  - Roundabout Papers, nos. I, III-X., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Proof sheets, with autograph corrections.
  - "Sorrows of Werther", 1853 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Autograph poem signed.
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld, 1982.
  - The Virginians, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Autograph manuscript notebook with twenty pages of notes, memoranda, and quotations on American history, materials used by Thackeray in writing The Virginians. On the preliminary two fly-leaves Thackeray has written his name and address, "36 Onslow Square, Brompton." The final leaf of the volume has an unfinished verse of poetry and a pencil sketch of Pocahontas rescuing Captain John Smith. On page 14 Thackeray transcribed a letter of his to Messrs. Sampson, Low & Son, referring to The Virginians, dated December 11, 1857. With an armorial bookplate of John and Dorothea Castles.
  - Lovel the Widower, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Proof sheets corrected by the author for publication in the The Cornhill Magazine, January-June 1860; bound.
  - Untitled play, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973; with bookplate of George Barr McCutcheon.
    Autograph manuscript fragment (2 pages) of an unpublished play, with autograph additions and corrections and note by Anne Thackeray Ritchie on front flyleaf; bound.
- Drawings, 1859-1878; Series III; 5
  Series III contains illustrations by the British illustrator/wood engraver John Priestman Atkinson, sketches by Thackeray, and a portrait of Thackeray by an unidentified artist.
  - Unidentified artist, Portrait of William Makepeace Thackeray; graphite on paper, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Related to a drypoint etching by George Barnett Smith.
    Gift of John W. Castles (Yale 1915), 1950.
  - Atkinson, J. Priestman, nine illustrations for chapters 3-8 and 10-12 of Cox's Diary; ink on paper, circa 1878 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Purchased on the Tinker Fund, 1973.
    Published in The Works of William Makepeace Thackeray ... v. 17 (London: Smith, Elder, 1879).
  - Atkinson, J. Priestman, four illustrations for Little Dinner at Timmin's; ink on paper, circa 1878 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Published in The Works of William Makepeace Thackeray ... v. 12 (London: Smith, Elder, 1879).
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace, three sketches; graphite on paper, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld, 1976.
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace, thirteen sketches; watercolor and graphite on paper, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Figure sketches and still life drawings from Thackeray's time in Bonn and other locations in Germany, with captions and notations.